Finding Aid for University of Michigan Architectural Drawings 1838-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University of Michigan Architectural Drawings
1838-1979
University of Michigan.
Blueprints, renderings, and blue-line prints of original University structures, and additions to, and alterations of existing structures. Architects and architectural firms represented include: Albert Kahn, Alexander J. Davis, Pond and Pond, C. William Palmer, and William LeBaron Jenney.
861158; Bimu;2
17 oversize folders in 3 blueprint cabinet drawers
1 blueprints
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The drawings came from different sources, but manly from the U-M department of buildings and grounds.
The collection is open for research.
This collection of University of Michigan architectural blueprints, renderings, and blueline prints has been drawn together from different sources. The provenance is not always clear, though most of the sheets probably originated with the Buildings and Grounds Department of the University. The collection is selective and does not include all campus buildings. Significant buildings are included, however, as are important architects and architectural firms. Represented in the collection are the works of Albert Kahn, Alexander J. Davis, Pond and Pond, the Chicago architectural firm, C. William Palmer, William L. Jenney, and York and Sawyer of New York.
Subjects:
Administration Building (University of Michigan); Alumni Center (University of Michigan); Angell Hall (University of Michigan); Ann Arbor High School (Mich.); Architects.; Architecture.; Art Building (University of Michigan); Burton Tower (University of Michigan); Central Service and Stack Building (University of Michigan); Dormitories--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; East Medical Building (University of Michigan); Engineering Shops Building (University of Michigan); Frieze Building (University of Michigan); Gymnasiums--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Haven Hall (University of Michigan: 1863-1950); Historic buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Hutchins Hall (University of Michigan); Legal Research Building (University of Michigan); Margaret Bell Pool (University of Michigan); Mason Hall (University of Michigan: 1841-1950); Michigan League.; Michigan Stadium (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Michigan Union.; Natural Science Building (University of Michigan); President's House (University of Michigan); School of Music Building (University of Michigan: Proposed); Simpson Memorial Institute (University of Michigan); Stockwell Hall (University of Michigan); Student Christian Association Building (University of Michigan); Tappan Hall (University of Michigan); University Hall (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Buildings.Buildings.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Library.; University of Michigan. Matthaei Botanical Gardens.; University of Michigan. School of Business Administration.; University of Michigan--Student housing.Student housing.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.; Waterman Gymnasium (University of Michigan); Women's Athletic Building (University of Michigan)
Contributors:
Albert Kahn Associated Architects & Engineers, Inc.; Bailey, Vernon Howe, 1874-1953.; Black and Black.; Cobb, Henry Ives, 1859-1931.; Colvin, Robinson and Associates.; Dahlstrom and Schmitz.; Davis, Alexander Jackson, 1803-1892.; Fry, Lynn W., 1894-1976.; Fry and Kasurin.; Giffels & Vallet, and Rossetti.; Harley, Ellington & Day.; Hubel, R. W.; Jenney, William Le Baron, 1832-1907.; Kahn, Albert, 1869-1942.; Loree, Douglas D.; Malcomson & Higginbotham, architects.; Otis and Clark (Chicago, Ill.); Palmer, C. William, 1886-1965.; Pond & Pond Architects.; Van Brunt and Howe (Boston, Mass.); Ware and Van Brunt (Boston, Mass.); York & Sawyer.
Genre/Form:
Architectural drawings.
- Architectural drawings
  - Administration Building. Harley, Ellington, and Day, architects, 1944; One pencil and ink rendering on paper (Map-case 1, Folder 1)
  - Administration Building for Proposed Engineering Research Group. Architect unknown, Undated; Two negative photographic copies of renderings (Map-case 1, Folder 1)
  - Angell Hall Addition. Lynn W. Fry, supervising architect, Undated; Four charcoal renderings on paper (Map-case 1, Folder 1)
  - College of Architecture and Design. New Art Center. Architect unknown, 1958; Six black-line prints, including one rendering, one site plan, and four floor plans (Map-case 1, Folder 1)
  - Art Building Study. Henry Ives Cobb, architect, 1899; Two watercolor renderings on paper (Map-case 1, Folder 2)
  - Proposed Astronomy Group on Base Lake. Buildings and Grounds Department designers., Two sheets, including one colored pencil rendered site plan on paper, and one positive print rendering (Map-case 1, Folder 2)
  - Botanical Gardens and Arboretum. Alger Dahlstrom and Herbert Schmitz, architects, undated; Two sheets, including photographic negative and positive copies of aerial perspectives (Map-case 1, Folder 2)
  - Burton Tower. Vernon Howe Bailey, artist, undated; One ink sketch rendering on paper (Map-case 1, Folder 2)
  - Business Administration, proposed school. Black and Black, architects, undated; Three floor plans in ink (Map-case 1, Folder 2)
  - Central Service and Stack Building. Albert Kahn, architect, 1953; One colored pencil rendering on paper (Map-case 1, Folder 2)
  - Church Street and East University Science Building. [on the site of present Physics and Astronomy Building]. Giffels & Vallet, and Rossetti, architects, undated; Four sheets, including perspectives, site plan, and floor plans; contain photographs of models, one rendering, and black-line prints (Map-case 1, Folder 3)
  - Detroit Observatory Residence, 1905; Six floor plans (Map-case 1, Folder 3)
  - Dramatic Arts. R. W. Hubel, architect, 1923; One colored pencil rendering on illustration board (Map-case 1, Folder 3)
  - East Medical Building. Albert Kahn, architect, 1927; Five blueline prints of floor plans (Map-case 1, Folder 3)
  - Old Engineering Shops. Buildings and Grounds Department, undated; Three floor plans done in pencil on tracing paper (Map-case 1, Folder 4)
  - Engineering College, Proposed Future Development. Buildings and Grounds Department, undated; One positive print of colored pencil aerial rendering (Map-case 1, Folder 4)
  - Engineering Shops Tower and Dormer. Buildings and Grounds Department, 1917; Four sheets, including elevations, plan, and section done in pencil on tracing paper (Map-case 1, Folder 4)
  - Field House for Signal Corps. Buildings and Grounds Department, 1918; Two sheets, including elevations, sections, plans, and details done in ink on tracing linen (Map-case 1, Folder 4)
  - Gymnasiums. Buildings and Grounds Department, 1927; Three photographic positive prints of floor plans (Map-case 1, Folder 4)
  - Haven Hall. Buildings and Grounds Department, 1935-1937; Four blueprints of floor plans (Map-case 1, Folder 4)
  - Hutchins Hall. York and Sawyer, architects, 1930; Three prints of pencil renderings (Map-case 1, Folder 4)
  - Albert Kahn unidentified building. Albert Kahn, architect, pre-1928, One-pencil and watercolor drawing of front elevation on Illustration board (Map-case 1, Folder 4)
  - Law School. York and Sawyer, architects, undated; One blueprint of site plan (Map-case 1, Folder 4)
  - League. Pond and Pond, architects, 1926; Four blueprints of floor plans (Map-case 1, Folder 4)
  - Legal Research Building. York and Sawyer, architects, 1929; One print of pencil rendering (Map-case 1, Folder 4)
  - Library Addition study. Albert Kahn, architect, 1947; Five renderings, including pencil, ink, and watercolor renderings on illustration board; and positive print of colored pencil rendering (Map-case 2, Folder 5)
  - Main Building. Building and Grounds Department, 1914; Two sheets, including floor plan and details done in ink on tracing linen (Map-case 2, Folder 5)
  - Mason Hall proposal. Alexander J. Davis, architect, 1838; Two floor plans done in pencil and ink on paper (Map-case 2, Folder 5)
  - Mason Hall. Board of Regents Building Committee, 1840; Four sheets, including three floor plans, done in ink on paper and one positive photograph of rendering (Map-case 2, Folder 5)
  - Medical Campus, undated; One aerial photograph of a model (Map-case 2, Folder 5)
  - Michigan Game Room. Pond and Pond, architects, undated; One gouache on paper (Map-case 2, Folder 6)
  - Michigan Union. Pond and Pond, architects, 1916; Four renderings, including three done in ink on paper tracings, and one ink on paper print (Map-case 2, Folder 6)
  - Music (Proposed School of). Architect unknown, undated; One rendering done in ink on paper (Map-case 2, Folder 7)
  - Natural Science. Architect unknown, undated; One floor plan of auditorium seating done in ink on linen tracing (Map-case 2, Folder 7)
  - Natural Science Building. Albert Kahn, architect, undated; 2 items (Map-case 2, Folder 7)
    (see also rolled blueprints)
  - Nurses Central Residence. Albert Kahn, architect, undated; Two renderings, charcoal and water color tracing (Map-case 2, Folder 7)
  - University of Michigan President's House. Buildings and Grounds Department, 1920; Nine blueprints of plans for remodeling, including three perspectives and six floor plans (Map-case 2, Folder 7)
  - President's House Additions. Albert Kahn, architect, 1932; Ten blueprints (Map-case 2, Folder 7)
  - Science Building. Room No. 475. Sound proof room. Buildings and Grounds Department, 1917., Two blueprints of plans, sections, and details (Map-case 2, Folder 7)
  - Simpson Memorial Institute. Albert Kahn, architect, circa 1925; One rendering done in colored pencil on tracing paper (Map-case 2, Folder 8)
  - University of Michigan Stadium. Press Box Elevation. Bernard L. Green, civil engineer, 1927; One blueprint, including one perspective and details (Map-case 2, Folder 8)
  - University of Michigan Stadium. Radio Booth. Bernard L. Green, civil engineer, 1927; One blueprint of details (Map-case 2, Folder 8)
  - University of Michigan. Storehouse and shops. Buildings and Grounds Department, 1929; Four blue-line prints, including three floor plans and one section (Map-case 2, Folder 8)
  - Student Christian Association Building. Otis and Clark, architects, 1916; Three blueprints of furniture layout plans (Map-case 2, Folder 8)
  - Tappan Hall. Architect unknown, undated; Four sheets, pencil on tracing paper, undated, including one rendering and three floor plans (Map-case 2, Folder 8)
  - University Hall. Proposed theater. Buildings and Grounds Department, 1914; Three ink on linen tracings, including two sections and one plan (Map-case 2, Folder 9)
  - University Hall Extension office cabinet. Buildings and Grounds Department, 1917; One ink on linen tracing of elevation (Map-case 2, Folder 9)
  - University Hall. South wing. Secretary's office remodeling. Buildings and Grounds Department, 1919; Two ink on linen tracings, including floor plans, details, and an elevation (Map-case 2, Folder 9)
  - University Hall. Seating plan. Buildings and Grounds Department, 1920; One floor plan done in ink on linen tracing (Map-case 2, Folder 9)
  - University Hall. Buildings and Grounds Department, 1927; Four blue-line prints of floor plans (Map-case 2, Folder 9)
  - University Hall. Auditorium. Buildings and Grounds Department, undated; One floor plan done in pencil on paper tracing (Map-case 2, Folder 9)
  - University Hospital. Homeopathic Ward. W.L. Jenney, architect, 2 items; ink on linen (Map-case 2, Folder 9)
  - Waterman Gymnasium. University Department of Buildings and Grounds, 1915; Two pencil on paper tracings, including one plan, sections, and details; see also additional drawings in drawer 3 (Map-case 2, Folder 9)
  - Women's Athletic Building. Pry and Kasurin, architects, undated; One rendering done in charcoal on paper tracing (Map-case 2, Folder 9)
  - Women's Dormitory. C. William Palmer, architect, 1938; Three photographic negatives of renderings (Map-case 2, Folder 9)
  - Waterman Gymnasium (Map-case 3)
    (See also separately located tube)
  - Henderson Memorial House. Douglas D. Loree, original architect. Colvin, Robinson, and Associates, architects, 1941-1958; Forty-five blueprint and blue-line prints, including plans, details, elevations, and sections
    - Preliminary study from Observatory Street, 1941; Five blueprint sheets, including one perspective and four floor plans (Map-case 3)
    - Observatory Street plans (plans inactivated in 1940), 1941; Nine blueprint sheets, including one plot and grading plan, one foundation plan, three floor plans, and four elevations (Map-case 3)
    - Building survey for Hill Street site, undated; Seven blueprint sheets, including four floor plans and three exterior elevations (Map-case 3)
    - Additions and Alterations, 1950; Eighteen blue-line prints, including one plot plan, four floor plans, three elevations, four details, two mechanical, one electrical, and three mechanical and electrical plans (Map-case 3)
    - Additions and Alterations, 1957; Three blue-line prints, including details, plans, elevations, and sections (Map-case 3)
    - Additions and Alterations, 1950; Three blue-line prints, including details, plans, elevations, and sections (Map-case 3)
  - Library Building Study. Van Brunt and Howe, architects, 1881; Sixteen sheets, including seven perspectives, one detail elevation, two details, one section, and five plans (in ink on linen) (Map-case 3)
  - Physical Science Laboratory. Albert Kahn, architect, 1922; Twenty-three blueprints, including twelve floor plans, one roof plan, six elevations, three details, one site plan containing include revisions (Map-case 3)
  - University Hall. Architect unknown, 1922., Eight blueprint sheets of floor plans (Map-case 3)
  - University Museum. William LeBaron Jenney, architect, 1879; 22 sheets of elevations, floor plans, and structural plans done in ink on linen
    - One front elevation (Map-case 3)
    - Rear elevation (Map-case 3)
    - One south side elevation (Map-case 3)
    - One north elevation (Map-case 3)
    - One large-scale elevation of part of front (Map-case 3)
    - One front exterior elevation and section with window details (Map-case 3)
    - One exterior elevation with detail of rear gable and elevator tower (Map-case 3)
    - One structural section and details (Map-case 3)
    - Two sections through foundation (Map-case 3)
    - One plan of roof framing (Map-case 3)
    - One gallery floor plan (Map-case 3)
    - First and second floor lighting and electrical plans (Map-case 3)
    - One attic floor plan (Map-case 3)
    - Two attic framing plans (Map-case 3)
    - One basement plan with floor joists of floor above (first floor framing plan) (Map-case 3)
    - First floor framing plan (Map-case 3)
    - Two gallery framing plans (Map-case 3)
    - One iron diagram no. 1 (Map-case 3)
  - Ann Arbor High School [Frieze Building]. Malcomson and Higginbotham, architects, 1905; Thirty-four ink on tracing paper sheets, including elevations, plans, sections, details. Ink on tracing paper (Map-case 3)
  - Alumni Center. Hugh Newall Jacobsen, architect, 1979; Eight sepia prints, and eight reversed image sepia prints, including floor plans and elevations (Map-case 3)
  - Margaret Bell Pool, 1951 (Map-case 3)
  - Natural Science Building. Albert Kahn, architect, 1914; Nine rolled blueprint sheets, including floor plans, sections, details, and elevations) Roll 42 (Tube 1)